Register of the Dymitr Hessen papers
Hoover Institution Archives
Dymitr Hessen papers,
1908-2002
2002C44
Hoover Institution Archives
4 manuscript boxes (1.6 linear feet)
Correspondence, writings, printed matter, personal documents, and photographs, relating to literature and philosophy. Includes papers of Sergei Gessen, father of Dymitr Hessen.
Hessen, Dymitr
Access
Collection is open for research.
The Hoover Institution Archives only allows access to copies of audiovisual items. To listen to sound recordings or to view videos or films during your visit, please contact the Archives at least two working days before your arrival. We will then advise you of the accessibility of the material you wish to see or hear. Please note that not all audiovisual material is immediately accessible.
Acquisition Information
Acquired by the Hoover Institution Archives in 2002.
Accruals
Materials may have been added to the collection since this finding aid was prepared. To determine if this has occurred, find the collection in Stanford University's online catalog at http://searchworks.stanford.edu/. Materials have been added to the collection if the number of boxes listed in the online catalog is larger than the number of boxes listed in this finding aid.
Biographical Note
Dymitr Hessen was a Polish-Russian literary scholar and co-author of the Wielki Slownik Polsko-Rosyjski, Rosyjsko-Polski.
Scope and Content of Collection
The papers of Dymitr Hessen reflect his writings and research interests in Russian émigré literature in the form of correspondence, notes, and printed matter. The collection also includes correspondence and literary and biographical materials relating to Hessen's father, Sergiusz (Sergei) Iosifovich Hessen, and his brother, Evgenii Sergeevich Hessen, as well as writings of two other émigrés, Solomon Bart and Vladimir Mansvetov.
Gessen, Sergei Iosifovich, 1887-1950.; Philosophy.; Polish literature.; Russian literature.
- Dymitr (Dmitrii) Sergeevich Hessen File, 1918-2001
  - Biographical File, 1944-2001
    Arrangement Statement
    Arranged by physical form, then chronologically.
    - Passport and other identification documents, 1944-1988 (Box-folder 1: 1-2)
    - Photograps depicting the Hessen family, 1944-2001 (Box-folder 1: 3)
      Scope and Contents note
      Includes pencil sketched portraits.
    - "Le diplôme d'Honneur," Jerusalem, Israel, 1984 (Box-folder 1: 4)
    - Death certificate, 2001 (Box-folder 1: 5)
  - Correspondence, 1938-2001
    Arranged alphabetically by correspondent.
    - General, 1945-1988 (Box-folder 1: 6)
    - Antonovich, Marko, 1981-1997 (Box-folder 1: 7)
    - Brandt, Hanes-Heinrich, 1984-1997 (Box-folder 1: 8)
    - Czistiakowa, Natalia, 2001 (Box-folder 1: 9)
    - Falk, Lilian, 1990-2001 (Box-folder 1: 10)
    - Fleishman, Lazar', 1999-2000 (Box-folder 1: 11)
    - Hessen, A., 2000 (Box-folder 1: 12)
    - Kaminski, Roman, circa 1945 (Box-folder 1: 13)
    - Malakhova, Galina, 1983-1997 (Box-folder 1: 14)
    - Mansvetov, Vladimir, 1938-1974 (Box-folder 1: 15)
      Includes clippings.
    - Uspenskii, Kirill, 1981-1983 (Box-folder 1: 16)
  - Writings, 1935-2000 (Box-folder 1: 17-21)
    Contains "Primechaniia k arkhivnym dokumentam D. Hessena," notes, correspondence and printed matter.
  - Research material, 1918-1998 (Box-folder 2: 1-6)
    Consists of articles, clippings, and other printed matter largely pertaining to Russian émigré literature.
- Evgenii Sergeevich Hessen File, 1924-1937
  Scope and Contents
  Comprised of documents regarding Dymitr Hessen's brother. Arranged in two groups by format.
  - Writing, poetry, and notes, 1924-1937 (Box-folder 2: 7-10)
    Includes letters from Vadim Morkovits to Sergiusz (Sergei) Hessen.
  - Diary, 1931 (Box-folder 2: 11)
- Sergiusz (Sergei) Iosifovich Hessen File, 1908-1959
  Comprised of documents regarding Dymitr Hessen's father.
  - Correspondence, 1923-1950
    Arranged in two groups, then chronologically.
    - General, 1944-1950 (Box-folder 2: 11)
    - Letters to his son, Dymitr Hessen, 1923-1950 (Box-folder 2: 12-19)
  - Writings, 1908-1959
    Arranged chronologically.
    - "Bibliografia prac Sergiusza Hessena,", 1908-1959 (Box-folder 3: 1-3)
    - "Chowanna," typescript, 1934 (Box-folder 3: 4)
    - Poetry, circa 1935 (Box-folder 3: 5)
    - "Modern Democracy," manuscript and typescript, circa 1945 (Box-folder 3: 6-7)
    - "Moia zhizn,'" and other biographical writings, 1945 (Box-folder 3: 8-9)
    - "Historia filozofii greckiej ze specjalnym uwzglednienien problematyki wychowania," typescript of lectures, 1945-1946 (Box-folder 3: 10-11, 4: 1)
    - Les droits de l'homme dans le libéralisme, le socialisme et le communisme, 1947 (Box-folder 4: 2)
    - Le droit et la moralite, 1953 (Box-folder 4: 3)
    - Notes, 1935-1946 (Box-folder 4: 4-5)
- Writings by Others, 1915-2002
  Arranged alphabetically by name of author.
  - Bart, Solomon, poems, memoirs, and correspondence, 1915-2002 (Box-folder 4: 6-10)
  - Daszkiewicz, Krystyna, 1987 (Box-folder 4: 11)
  - Gonec, Vladimir, 2000 (Box-folder 4: 12)
  - Kostsinskii, K., circa 1980 (Box-folder 4: 13)
  - Mansvetov, Vladimir, writings and correspondence, 1933-1974 (Box-folder 4: 14)